<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To my beloved wife Helener Penry partaker with me in this life of the suffrings of the gospel in the kingdome and pacience of Iesus Christ, and resting with me in vndowbted hope of the glory that shal-be revealed : all strenght and comfort, with all other spirituall graces be multiplyed through Christ Iesus our Lord.</title>
            <author>Penry, John, 1559-1593.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1593</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 17 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09297</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19610</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S1617</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">20236061</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 20236061</idno>
            <idno type="VID">23885</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09297)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 23885)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1711:29)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>To my beloved wife Helener Penry partaker with me in this life of the suffrings of the gospel in the kingdome and pacience of Iesus Christ, and resting with me in vndowbted hope of the glory that shal-be revealed : all strenght and comfort, with all other spirituall graces be multiplyed through Christ Iesus our Lord.</title>
                  <author>Penry, John, 1559-1593.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1593]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Signed: Your husband nowe for a season, and your beloved brother for evermore Ihon Penry -- P. [4].</note>
                  <note>Date of imprint suggested by STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: tightly bound with slight loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Trinity College (University of Cambridge). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Penry, Helener.</term>
               <term>Penry, John, 1559-1593.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:23885:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:23885:1"/>
            <head>TO MY BELOVED WIFE HELENER PENRY, partaker with me in this life of the ſuffrings of the Goſpel in the kingdome and pacience of Ieſus Chriſt: And reſting with me in vndowbted hope of the glory that ſhalbe revealed: all ſtrenght and comfort, with all other ſpirituall graces be multiplyed through Chriſt Ieſus our Lord.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
               </hi> ſee my blood layed for (my beloved) and ſo my daies and teſtimonies draw<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing to an end for ought I knowe: and therfore I think it my dutie to leave behinde me this teſtimonie of my love towards ſo deare a ſiſter and ſo loving a wife in the Lord as you have ben vnto me. Firſt then I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſech you ſtand faſt in that truth which you and I profeſſe at this preſent in much outward diſcomforte and danger. Let nothing drawe you to be ſubiect to antichriſt in anie of his ordinances. Let your ſoule and pour bodie be far fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thoſe aſſemblies which yelde either knowne or ſecrete ſubmiſſion vnto the ordinances of the beaſt. that is to receave his marks eyther in the right hand or the forhead / as the ſpirit of God ſayeth. <hi>Rev. 13.16.</hi> For this are you forbidden to doe vnder the payne of Gods eternal wrath. <hi>Rev. 14.9.10.11. 2 Cor. 6.14.15.16.</hi> &amp; <hi>1 Cor. 3.16.17. Rev. 22.18.19. Deu. 12.30.31.32. &amp;c.</hi> Againe (my beloved) / continewe a member of that holy ſocietie whereof nowe you are / where the Lord in his ordinances raigneth: for here and in all ſuch aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies the Lord dwelleth by the preſence and power of his ſpirit <hi>Mat. 18.20. &amp; 28.20. Exod. 29.45. Leui. 26.11.12.</hi> Here he is a mightie protection and defence readie at hand <hi>Iſay. 26.1. &amp; 4.6..</hi> And his ordinances you knowe / hath he greatlie comaunded to be kept and obſerved. <hi>Pſal. 119.4.</hi> Oh our ſoules are to reioyce in theſe waies more then in all ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance and treaſure <hi>Pſal. 119.14.</hi> And the loving kindnes of the eternall is for ever and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver towards them and theyr ſeed that remember his ordinances to doe them. <hi>Pſal. 103.17 18.</hi> Whereas all thoſe are accurſed that err from his ſtatutes and diminiſhe from the obe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dience they owe vnto his Maieſtie. <hi>Pſal. 119.21. Reu. 22:19. Pſal. 119.118.</hi> I pray you mark theſe places with all ſuch like in the word / againſt all thoſe that maketh a ſlayght matter eyther not to walke in the wayes of God or to be ſubiect vnto ſmall corruptions as they acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pte them &amp; be enarmed with the power of the word againſt all ſuch lying de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>luſions. Lok. <hi>2 Cor. 6.14.15.17.</hi> In concluſion my dear wife and ſiſter / loke not at a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie earthlie thingh / conſecrate your ſelfe wholly / both ſoule / bodie / huſband / children / and whatſoever you have vnto the Lord your God / let them not be dearer vnto you then his worſhip and ſervice / knowe / it knowe it to be an vnſpeakable preferment for you / that he voutchſafeth to take eyther your ſelfe / or anie of yours to ſuffer affictions with him and his goſpel here vpon earth. <hi>Luk. 18.30. Mat. 19.29.</hi> And I am perſwaded that you have vndergone the profeſſion of the truth vpon the condition ſet downe by our ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour Chriſt. <hi>Luk. 14.26.27.</hi> that is to hate all in reſpect of his goſpel. Fear not the want of outward things / for the Lord careth for you and yours. Remember what is ſet downe. <hi>Heb. 13.5. Luk. 12.31.</hi> The Lord is my God and yours / and the God of our ſeed. I knowe if you and our pore children continewe / that they ſhall ſee a bleſſed re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward eve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in this life for theſe ſmale and weak ſuffrings of ours for the intereſt and right of Chriſt Ieſus / for I am aſſuered that the Lord wil give a breathing time / a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable reſt vnto his pore Church in this life. And my good wife / if you or anie of mine live to ſee thoſe daies: reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber and let my pore children reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber to declare in Syon the vengeance of the Lord our God and the vengea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of his temple againſt babel: and that the Lord God hath brought forth our righteouſnes in rewarding that wicked antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian religion as it hath done vnto vs. <hi>Ier. 50.28. and 51.10.35.36. and 50.15. Reu. 18.6.</hi> In the meane tyme wait pacientlie the Lords leaſure / he is not forgetful of you and yours eſpeciallie of his pore Church / he cannot denie himſelf and the truth of his promiſes you know <hi>2 Tim. 6.5.</hi> Be much and often in prayer day and night / much in reading and medi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tation
<pb facs="tcp:23885:2"/>of his word / and you ſhall find that he will graunt you yours harts deſiere / accor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding to his good pleaſure &amp; will. Pray with your pore familie &amp; children morning and eavening as you doe. Inſtruct them and your maide in the good waies of God. See that no day paſſe over your head wherin you have not taught them (eſpecially her) ſome one principall of the truth. Think the tyme greatlie gained / as I have often told you that is ſpent in the word of the Lord. <hi>Pſal. 1.1.2. Ioſh. 1.8.</hi> Amongſt other places of the word wherin I would have you to be converſant in regard of theſe tymes / I pray you to read <hi>Mat. 10. Luc. 12. Iohn. 14.15.16. and 17.</hi> chapters. <hi>Pſal. 37. Iſay. 60.61.62.63.</hi> chapters: Marke everie day what petitions you make vnto the Lord / that you may have eyther ſtrenght and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort of your faith in the inioyng of the things you aſke and ſo may returne thank<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fulnes vnto him / or continewance of pacience in expecting and wayting for his mercie / And be not wearie in attending vpon his good leaſure / for in due tyme ſhall we receave if we faynt not / for yet a verie little while / and he that ſhall come will come and will not car<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e. <hi>Heb. 10.37.</hi> Above all things pray that the Lord would reſtore bewtie vnto his Church and ſo would overthrowe the curſed religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Gomaine Antichriſt in everie parte thereof / obſerve your owne eſpeciall infirmeties and wants / and be earneſt with the Lord that he would doe them away / and conſume them by the power of his ſpirit. Remember me alſo and my brethren nowe in bonds / that the Lord would aſſiſt vs with the ſtrenght and comfort of his ſpirit to kepe a good conſcience and to beare a glorious teſtimonie vnto the end: yea be not void of hope / but I may be reſtored agayne vnto you by your praiers / and therfore alſo be earneſt with him for my delivera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. If the Lord ſhall end my days in this teſtimonie / as bleſſed be his name howſoever it goeth / I am readie and content with his good pleaſure / kepe your ſelf my good Helen here with this pore Church / you may make as good refuge and ſtay here as anie where elſe for your ou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tward eſtate / though you could not / yet I knowe that you had rather dwell vnder the wings of the God of Iſraell in povertie with godlie Ruth / then to poſſeſſe kingdomes out of the land of Canaan / and whatſoever ſhift you make kepe our pore children with you that you may bring them vp your ſelfe in the inſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and informatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Lord <hi>Epheſ. 6.4.</hi> I leave you and them indeed nothing in this life / but the bleſſing of my God and his bleſſed promyſes made vnto me a pore wretched ſinner / that my ſeed / my habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and familie ſhould be bleſſed and happie vpon the earth / and this my ſiſter I dout not ſhalbe fownd an ample portion both for you and them / though you knowe that in hunger often in could often / in povertie and nakednes we muſt make an accompt to pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>feſſe the Goſpell in this life. And teach them I beſeech you even nowe in their youth that leſſon indeede / which was the laſt that I taught them in word / and that is / that / If they will raigne with Chriſt they muſt ſuffer with him: and acquaynt them now in theyr youth with the baſenes and meanes of the Goſpel: teach them that they are not to loke for great things in this life / but everie day to make accompt that they are to yeeld theyr lyves and whatſoever they have for the truth. Break their affections betymes while they are yet greene / by inſtructions out of the word and corrections meet for them yet you knowe that parents muſt not be bitter vnto their children. <hi>Eph. 6.4.</hi> eſpeciallie ſmiete not the elder child over hard / becauſe you knowe the leaſt word will reſtrayne her / when they are capabell of anie handie labour / I knowe you will not let them be idell Yf poſſiebell you ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / let them learne / both to read and alſo to wryte / howſoever it be whe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther theyr bringing vp be better or worſe vnder your hand or under the hands of others I their father doe here chardge them whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they come to yeares of diſcretio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as they ſhall anſwer in that great daie of iudgement that they ioyne themſelves with the true profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and Church of Chriſt / wherin nowe I goe before them / the which charge of myne that they may kepe / I beſech you my good wife to put them often in mynde of the fame and what a bleſſing will enſue vnto them if they keepe it / as alſo what a iudgement will ſurelie followe if they neglect it. <hi>Ier. 15.18.</hi> And withal be carefull in caſe you ſhould not be able to kepe them all with you that they be brought vp with ſome of the Church with bread and water rather then be clad with gould with anie (howe forward ſoever they ſeeme to profeſſe) that yeeld anie obedience vnto the antichriſtian ordinances / for
<pb facs="tcp:23885:2"/>with ſuch they cannot chuſe but be leveaned with corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. I knowe my good Helen that the burden which I laie vpon thee of. <hi>4.</hi> infa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts wherof the elder is not. <hi>4.</hi> years olde will not ſeeme anie wiſe burdenſome vnto thee / yea thou ſhalt fynd that our God willbe a father vnto the fatherleſſe and a ſtaie vnto the widowe.</p>
            <p>But here my moſt dear ſiſter and wife / I agaiene adviſe you not to be a widowe long after my daies / for you knowe the ordinance of God / that it is good for a man not to be alone / ſo is it a great bleſſing for a woman to have an head. And although to be maried bringeth care and troble with it outwardlie / yet is that holie order accompanied with that comfort in this life / as of all outward things I judg it to be one of the greateſt bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings for man or woman to be maried in the Lord if they cannot conteine. Onelie take heed in your choyſe / that firſt he with whom you match be of the ſame holy faith and profeſſion with you / next that he be meet to be your h<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ad / even ſuch a one as you think fit to governe you as a head and rule you as a Lord: And in this choiſe loke not vnto welth or eſtimation in the world / yet rather chuſe many bleſſings then one if you may but onelie reſpect the feare of God and the meetnes of the party. Thus having hether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto diſburdened my ſelf of my dutie towards you and care over you and your pore chil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dren / in ſome part / nowe to come vnto my ſelfe / I am I thank my God in great comfort in him though vnder great trialls of my weakneſſes / not for feare of anie fleſh I thank my God but in conſideration of myne owne wants / rebellion / diſobedience and vntha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>k<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fulnes vnto his maieſtie / but in regard of men and in reſpect of the cauſe of my GOD wherin I ſtand. I feare not anie power or ſtrenght of man whatſoever and I am this howre moſt willing to laie downe my life for the word of my teſtimony / and I truſt ſhall be onto the end. I was taken you knowe at Ratliffe the <hi>22.</hi> of the <hi>3.</hi> month March <hi>1592.</hi> caried the <hi>24.</hi> before M. yong comitted by him cloſe vnto the Counter Poultry: caried before M. Yong agayne the <hi>26.</hi> of the ſame month <hi>1593.</hi> wher was D. <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>angham and his brother preachers both / ſent as M. Yong ſayd by my Lord Keeper to confer with me. I anſwered that I reverenced the authoritie of my Lord Keeper and the reſt of her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties Counſel / but as for pryvate conference / in as much as my cauſe was made publik and that my adverſaries had my writtings in ther hands / wherby I moved the Parle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the cauſe / I ſaw no reaſon why I ſhould yeeld vnto any. I deſyred publike vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>quall conditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s: heare after great heat vttered by M. vaugham / and ſome warmnes on my part I was ſent agayne cloſe whence I came. The <hi>28.</hi> of the ſame month I was called for by M. Yong to confer with M. D. Balgue of the Temple / where agayne I deſyred an equall tryall ſet downe <hi>4.</hi> of the ſpeciall heads / and the conditions / toke a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py of them / and ſo departed / after manie reaſonable words given vnto me by M. Yong The <hi>2.</hi> of the <hi>5.</hi> month Aprill came M. D. Crook. M. Grennham and M. Temple vn<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the priſon to confer with me, both of chriſtian charitie / and alſo having authoritie ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto as they ſayd: I refuſed all private intermedling in ſo publik an action / ſhewed them the things offred by me vnto M. Yong and accepted for the tyme in good parte by him / demanded whether they had authority to condeſcend vnto thoſe equall conditions / and ſo I would confer with them or with any: They ſayd no: and therfore after much needles ſpeech departed / M. Temple very jniuriouſly taking away whether I would or not / the copy of that which I gave vnto M. Yong / wherof he ſent me a copy the <hi>5.</hi> of the ſame month but retayned myne owne. Vpon which day I was ſent for to the ſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons houſe wher was Syr Georg Barnes as I take it M. Yong M. Dale the Deane of weſtmynſter and an other of the Clargy / they offred me an othe which I refuſed becauſe it was againſt conſcience and lawe: proteſting notwithſtanding that I heald lawfull to take an othe before a magiſtrate: then they examined me of my going with Edward Graves / I a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſwered in deed that I lay at an jnn at Hodſden with him about the tyme then ſpake / but I would goe no f<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rther to anſwer them in this poynt thus far but no further I anſwered he<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> both becauſe they knewe of it before and eſpecially for ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reſpects then moving me. After this they dealt with me about my being in Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land
<pb facs="tcp:23885:3"/>and / in the middeſt of which diſcourſe they ſent me away / It was playne with the but eſpecially with M. Yong: Herin this is moſt memorable that alleaging Numb <hi>35. 33.</hi> they ſet it downe as an article againſt me though I read the very words vnto them they are ſo lamentablie ignorant / and lay wayt for blood ſo cruellie that certaynlie th<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Lords hande is not far of. The Lord ſhew mercy vnto vs and them / from my har<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> I wiſh it. I cannot ſee but that they thirſt after my blood: Therfore pray for me and deſyre all the Church to doe the ſame.</p>
            <p>To drawe to an end / ſalute the whole Church from me eſpeciallie thoſe in bunds / and be you all much and hartely ſaluted in the Lord. Let none of you be diſmayed. Th<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> Lord will ſend a glorious iſſue to Syons troubles. Yet you muſt all be prepared for ſuf<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>frings / I ſee no other likelyhood: Let not thoſe which are abroad myſſe to frequen<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> the holy meetings: Salute my mother and yours in Wales: my brethren / ſyſters an<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> kindered ther. And my God knoweth / yea your ſelf knoweth howe earneſtlie and of<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ten I have deſyred that he would voutchſafe my ſervice in his Goſpell among them t<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> the winning of ther ſoules for evermore vnto him. Salute your parents and myne i<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> Northampthone / with my poore Kinſma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Ienkin Iones and M. David alſo / thoug<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> I had not thought that anie owtward reſpects would have made him withdrawe hi<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> ſhowlders from the Lords wayes / but the Lord will drawe him forward in his goo<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> tyme. Salute all ours in Scotland vpon the borders and every way northward / eſpe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cially M. I<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ell / always deare vnto me. Chriſt Ieſus bleſſe thee and them all my belo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ved even for ever and ever. Let it not be knowne vnto anie ſave vnto the party tha<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> ſhall read this vnto you / that I have written at all as yet / I gote meanes this day t<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> writte thus much wherof no creature lyving knoweth. The <hi>6.</hi> of the <hi>4.</hi> month April <hi>1593.</hi> in great haſte with manie teares and yet in the great ſpirituall comfort of my ſoule</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your huſband nowe for a ſeaſon / and your beloved brother for evermore Ihon Penry an vnworthy witneſſe of Chriſts Teſtament / againſt the abhominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Roman Antichriſt and his ſouldyers / ſure of the victory by the blood of the lamb.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:23885:3"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
